<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
<!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
<!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
<!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-rpc-rfc7322bis-00" category="info" submissionType="editorial" obsoletes="7322" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC Style Guide (rfc7322bis)">RFC Style Guide</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-rpc-rfc7322bis-00"/>
    <author initials="S." surname="Ginoza" fullname="Sandy Ginoza">
      <organization>RFC Production Center</organization>
      <address>
        <email>sginoza@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

      <author initials="J." surname="Mahoney" fullname="Jean Mahoney">
      <organization>RFC Production Center</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jmahoney@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	  
      <author initials="A." surname="Russo" fullname="Alice Russo">
      <organization>RFC Production Center</organization>
      <address>
        <email>arusso@amsl.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	  
	  
    <date month="May" day="1" year="2023"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the fundamental and unique style conventions
and editorial policies currently in use for the RFC Series.  It
captures the RFC Editor's basic requirements and offers guidance
regarding the style and structure of an RFC.  Additional guidance is
captured on a website that reflects the experimental nature of that
guidance and prepares it for future inclusion in the RFC Style Guide.
This document obsoletes RFC 7322, "RFC Style Guide".</t>
	    <t>Note: This draft is being developed and discussed in the GitHub repo 
	    <eref brackets="angle" target="https://github.com/rfc-editor/draft-rpc-rfc7322bis" />,
	    but any substantive change should be discussed on <eref brackets="angle" target="rfc-interest@rfc-interest.org" />.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>The ultimate goal of the RFC publication process is to produce
documents that are readable, clear, and consistent.  The basic formatting
conventions for RFCs were established
in the 1970s by the original RFC Editor, Jon Postel.  This document
describes the fundamental and unique style conventions and editorial
policies currently in use for the RFC Series <xref target="RFC4844" format="default"/> and is
intended as a stable, infrequently updated reference for authors,
editors, and reviewers.</t>
      <t>The RFC Editor also maintains a web portion of the Style Guide (see
Appendix A.3) that describes issues as they are raised and indicates
how the RFC Editor intends to address them.  As new style issues
arise, the RFC Editor will first address them on the web portion of
the Style Guide <xref target="STYLE-WEB" format="default"/>.  These topics may become part of the RFC
Style Guide when it is revised.</t>
      <t>The world of publishing has generally accepted rules for
grammar, punctuation, capitalization, sentence length and complexity, etc.
The RFC Editor generally follows these accepted
rules as defined by the Chicago Manual of Style (CMOS) <xref target="CMOS" format="default"/>, with a
few important exceptions to avoid ambiguity in complex technical
prose and to handle mixtures of text and computer languages, or to
preserve historical formatting rules.  This document presents these
exceptions as applied or recommended by the RFC Editor.</t>
      <t>All RFCs begin as Internet-Drafts (also referred to as I-Ds), and a
well-written and properly constructed Internet-Draft <xref target="ID-GUIDE" format="default"/>
provides a strong basis for a good RFC.  The RFC Editor accepts
Internet-Drafts from specified streams for publication [RFC4844] and
applies the rules and guidelines for the RFC Series during the
editorial process.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="rfc-editors-philosophy" toc="default">
      <name>RFC Editor's Philosophy</name>
      <t>Authors may find it helpful to understand the RFC Editor's goals
during the publication process, namely to:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>Prepare the document according to RFC style and format.</li>
        <li>Make the document as clear, consistent, and readable as possible.</li>
        <li>Correct larger content/clarity issues; flag any unclear passages
for author review.</li>
        <li>Fix inconsistencies (e.g., terms that appear in various forms,
 inconsistent capitalization, discrepancies between a figure and the text that
 describes it).</li>
      </ul>
      <t>We strive for consistency within:</t>
      <t>a. the document,</t>
      <t>b. a cluster of documents <xref target="CLUSTER" format="default"/>, and</t>
      <t>c. the series of RFCs on the subject matter.</t>
      <t>The editorial process of the RFC Editor is not an additional
technical review of the document.  Where the RFC Editor may suggest
changes in wording for clarity and readability, it is up to the
author, working group, or stream-approving body to determine whether
the changes have an impact on the technical meaning of the document
[RFC4844].  If the original wording is a more accurate representation
of the technical content being described in the document, it takes
precedence over editorial conventions.</t>
      <t>The activity of editing sometimes creates a tension between author
and editor.  The RFC Editor attempts to minimize this conflict for
RFC publication while continually striving to produce a uniformly
excellent document series.  The RFC Editor refers to this fundamental
tension as "editorial balance," and maintaining this balance is a
continuing concern for the RFC Editor.  There is a prime directive
that must rule over grammatical conventions: do not change the
intended meaning of the text.</t>
      <t>If the RFC Editor cannot edit a document without serious risk of
altering the meaning, it may be returned to the stream-approving body
for review.  See Appendix A.2 for more information.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="rfc-style-conventions" toc="default">
      <name>RFC Style Conventions</name>
      <t>This Style Guide does not use terminology as defined in <xref target="RFC2119" /> and <xref target="RFC8174" />.  In this document, lowercase use of "must" and "should"
indicates changes the RFC Editor will make automatically to conform
with this Style Guide versus those that may be questioned if not
applied.  The lowercase "must" indicates those changes that will be
applied automatically and are not at the discretion of the authors.
The lowercase "should" indicates the RFC Editor's recommended use,
but conformance with the recommendations is not required; the RFC
Editor may question whether the guidance may be applied.</t>
      <section anchor="language" toc="default">
        <name>Language</name>
        <t>The RFC publication language is English.  Spelling may be either
American or British, as long as an individual document is internally
consistent.  Where both American and British English spelling are
used within a document or cluster of documents, the text will be
modified to be consistent with American English spelling.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="punctuation" toc="default">
        <name>Punctuation</name>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>
            <t>A comma is used before the last item of a series, e.g.,  </t>
            <t>
"TCP service is reliable, ordered, and full duplex"</t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>When quoting literal text, punctuation is placed outside quotation
marks, e.g.,  </t>
            <t>
Search for the string "Error Found".  </t>
            <t>
When quoting general text, such as general text from another RFC,
punctuation may be included within the quotation marks, e.g.,  </t>
            <t>
RFC 4844 indicates that "RFCs are available free of charge to
   anyone via the Internet." </t>
            <t>
Quotation marks are not necessary when text is formatted as a
block quotation.</t>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <section anchor="compounds" toc="default">
          <name>RFCs as Compounds</name>
          <t>Whenever possible:
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>Hyphenated compounds formed with RFC numbers should be avoided;
      this can be accomplished by: rewording the sentence (e.g., change "[RFC5011]-style
      rollover" to "rollover as described in RFC 5011"). </li>
            <li>adding a note in either the Terminology or Conventions section mentioning
      the RFC so that other occurrences throughout the text will be understood by
      the reader to be in the style of said RFC (e.g., This document uses the term
      "rollover" as defined in RFC 5011.).</li>
          </ul>
          <t>If use of an RFC number in attributive position is unavoidable, the
      preferred form should appear as in the example "RFC 5011-style rollover".
      That is:
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>no hyphen between "RFC" and the number (don't use RFC-5011-style rollover)</li>
            <li>avoid hyphenating citations with text (don't use [RFC5011]-style rollover)</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="dns-names-and-uris" toc="default">
        <name>DNS Names and URIs</name>
        <t>DNS names, whether or not in URIs, that are used as generic examples
in RFCs should use the particular examples defined in "Reserved Top
Level DNS Names" <xref target="BCP32" format="default"/>, to avoid accidental conflicts.</t>
        <t>Angle brackets are strongly recommended around URIs <xref target="STD66" format="default"/>, e.g.,</t>
        <t>&lt;https://example.com/&gt;</t>
        <t>The use of HTTPS rather than HTTP is strongly encouraged.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="capitalization" toc="default">
        <name>Capitalization</name>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>Capitalization must be consistent within the document and ideally
should be consistent with related RFCs.  Refer to the online table
of decisions on consistent usage of terms in RFCs <xref target="TERMS" format="default"/>.</li>
          <li>Per CMOS guidelines, the major words in RFC titles and section
titles should be capitalized (this is sometimes called "title
case").  Typically, all words in a title will be capitalized,
except for internal articles, prepositions, and conjunctions.</li>
          <li>Section titles that are in sentence form will follow typical
sentence capitalization.</li>
          <li>Titles of figures may be in sentence form or use title case.</li>
          <li>Some terms related to the various roles or parts of the streams authoring
    RFCs should be used consistently.  For example, when the term 'working group'
    or 'research group' is used as part of a
    specific group name, it will be capitalized (e.g., kitten Working Group,
    Crypto Forum Research Group). When used to generally refer to groups, it
    will be downcased.</li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="citations" toc="default">
        <name>Citations</name>
        <t>The most important function of a citation is to point to a reference so that
a reader may follow up on additional material that is important in some way to
understanding or implementing the content in an RFC. This section offers guidance
on the requirements and recommendations for citation format within an RFC.</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>References and citations must match.  That is, there must be a
reference for each citation used, and vice versa.</li>
          <li>Citations must be enclosed in square brackets (e.g., "[CITE1]").</li>
          <li>Citations are restricted to ASCII-only characters, as described in "The Use
    of Non-ASCII Characters in RFCs" <xref target="RFC7997" format="default"/>.</li>
          <li>
            <t>Citations must begin with a number or a letter, and may contain digits, letters,
  colons, hyphens, underscores, or dots.
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>Example: "[IEEE.802.15.4]" rather than "[.802.15.4]"</li>
              <li>Example: "[RFC2119]" rather than "[RFC 2119]"</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>Citations may not include spaces, commas, quotation marks, or other
   punctuation (!, ?, etc.), and should be in-line with the normal line of type.
            </t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>Example: "See RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> for more information."</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Cross-references within the body of the memo and to other RFCs
must use section numbers rather than page numbers, as pagination
may change per format and device.</li>
          <li>
            <t>A citation may A) follow the subject to which the citation applies
    or B) be read as part of the text. For example:
            </t>
            <ol spacing="normal" type="a"><li>As part of the transition to IPv6, NAT64 [RFC6146] and DNS64
     [RFC6147] technologies will be utilized by some access networks to
     provide IPv4 connectivity for IPv6-only nodes [RFC6144].</li>
              <li>Note that SAVI raises a number of important privacy considerations
     that are discussed more fully in [RFC6959].</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
          <li>For a document referenced multiple times in running text, the citation anchor must
       be at first use outside the abstract. Additional citations are allowed at the author's
       discretion.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>We recommend using A) and strongly recommend consistent use of one style throughout.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="abbreviation-rules" toc="default">
        <name>Abbreviation Rules</name>
        <t>Abbreviations should be expanded in document titles and upon first
use in the document.  The full expansion of the text should be
followed by the abbreviation itself in parentheses.  The exception is
an abbreviation that is so common that the readership of RFCs can be
expected to recognize it immediately; examples include (but are not
limited to) TCP, IP, SNMP, and HTTP.  The online list of
abbreviations <xref target="ABBR" format="default"/> provides guidance.  Some cases are marginal, and
the RFC Editor will make the final judgment, weighing obscurity
against complexity.</t>
        <t>Note: The online list of abbreviations is not exhaustive or
   definitive.  It is a list of abbreviations appearing in RFCs and
   sometimes reflects discussions with authors, Working Group Chairs,
   and/or Area Directors (ADs).  Note that some abbreviations have
   multiple expansions.  Additionally, this list includes some terms
   that look like abbreviations but that are actually fixed names for
   things and hence cannot and should not be expanded.  These are
   noted as "No Expansion".</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="images" toc="default">
        <name>Images and Figures</name>
        <t>The goal of having images within an RFC is to convey information. A good
    diagram or image expresses information quickly, clearly, and with low chance
    of misunderstanding. Technically correct but confusing images get in the
    way of understanding and implementation.</t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1"><li>Images should be legible when displayed on a standard screen (1920x1080)
        and printable on either A4 or US Letter paper. Any text within the diagram
        should be readable at that resolution. </li>
          <li>Authors should use black on white, not white on black. No color or
        greyscale <xref target="RFC7990" format="default"/><xref target="RFC7996" format="default"/></li>
          <li>Keep your diagrams as simple as possible. If an object in the diagram
        is not immediately relevant, leave it out. If you have several ideas you
        want to convey, consider using more than one diagram.</li>
          <li>San-serif fonts are generally considered more readable for digital
        material. [citation needed]</li>
          <li>The style of diagrams within an RFC should be consistent both within a
        single RFC and within a cluster of RFCs (fonts, shapes,
        lines). For example, if you you use a dashed line to indicate a certain
        type of packet flow, then continue to use that style of line consistently.
        </li>
          <li>Line styles, including thickness, color, and arrow types, are easy
        methods to convey a particular meaning to the reader. Consistently use
        the same line styles to convey a particular meaning throughout all
        diagrams within an RFC in order to avoid confusing the reader.</li>
          <li>Flowcharts: avoid crossing the lines if possible.</li>
          <li>Captions or alternative text are encouraged for all figures, diagrams,
        and other artwork. <xref target="ALTTEXT" format="default"/>
            <xref target="RFC7991" format="default"/></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="structure-of-an-rfc" toc="default">
      <name>Structure of an RFC</name>
      <t>A published RFC will largely contain the elements in the following
list.  Some of these sections are required, as noted.  Those sections
marked with "*" will be supplied by the RFC Editor during the
editorial process when necessary. The rules for each of these elements are
described in more detail below.</t>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
First-page header                      * [Required]
Title                                    [Required]
Abstract                                 [Required]
RFC Editor or Stream Note              * [Upon request]
Status of This Memo                    * [Required]
Copyright Notice                       * [Required]
Table of Contents                      * [Required]
Body of the Memo                         [Required]

  1.  Introduction                       [Required]
  2.  Requirements Language (RFC 2119)
  3.  ...
       MAIN BODY OF THE TEXT
  6.  ...
  7.  IANA Considerations                [Required]
  8.  Internationalization Considerations
  9.  Security Considerations            [Required]
  10.  References
  10.1.  Normative References
  10.2.  Informative References
  Appendix A.
  Appendix B.

Acknowledgements
Contributors
Index
Author's Address                         [Required]

]]></artwork>
      <t>Within the body of the memo, the order shown above is strongly
recommended.  Exceptions may be questioned.  Outside the body of the
memo, the order above is required.  The section numbers above are for
illustrative purposes; they are not intended to correspond to
required numbering in an RFC.</t>
      <t>The elements preceding the body of the memo should not be numbered.
Typically, the body of the memo will have numbered sections and the
appendices will be labeled with letters.  Any sections that appear
after the appendices should not be numbered or labeled (e.g., see
"Contributors" above).</t>
      <section anchor="first-page-header" toc="default">
        <name>First-Page Header</name>
        <t>Headers will follow the format described in "RFC Streams, Headers,
and Boilerplates" <xref target="RFC7841" format="default"/> and its successors.  In addition, the
following conventions will apply.</t>
        <section anchor="authoreditor" toc="default">
          <name>Author/Editor</name>
          <t>The final determination of who should be listed as an author or editor on
an RFC is made by the stream, as is whether or not including author
affiliation is required.</t>
          <t>The author's name (initial followed by family name) appears on the
first line of the heading.  Some variation, such as additional
initials or capitalization of family name, is acceptable.  Once the
author has selected how their name should appear, they should use
that display consistently in all of their documents.</t>
          <t>The total number of authors or editors on the first page is generally
limited to five individuals and their affiliations.  If there is a
request for more than five authors, the stream-approving body needs
to consider if one or two editors should have primary responsibility
for this document, with the other individuals listed in the
Contributors or Acknowledgements section.  There must be a direct
correlation of authors and editors in the document header and the
Authors' Addresses section.  These are the individuals that must sign
off on the document during the AUTH48 process and respond to
inquiries, such as errata.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="organization" toc="default">
          <name>Organization</name>
          <t>The author's organization is indicated on the line following the
author's name.</t>
          <t>For multiple authors, each author name appears on its own line,
followed by that author's organization.  When more than one author is
affiliated with the same organization, the organization can be
"factored out," appearing only once following the corresponding
Author lines.  However, such factoring is inappropriate when it would
force an unacceptable reordering of author names.</t>
          <t>If an author cannot or will not provide an affiliation for any
reason, "Independent", "Individual Contributor", "Retired", or some
other term that appropriately describes the author's affiliation may
be used.  Alternatively, a blank line may be included in the document
header when no affiliation is provided.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="issn-2070-1721" toc="default">
          <name>ISSN: 2070-1721</name>
          <t>The RFC Series has been assigned an International Standard Serial
Number of 2070-1721 <xref target="ISO3297" format="default"/>.  It will be included by the
RFC Editor.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="doi-10-17487" toc="default">
          <name>Digital Object Identifier 10.17487</name>
	  <t>The RFC Series has been assigned a Digital Object Identifier prefix of
	     10.17487 <xref target="RFC7669" format="default"/>.  A DOI will be assigned and included by the
RFC Editor.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="updates-and-obsoletes" toc="default">
          <name>Updates and Obsoletes</name>
          <t>When an RFC obsoletes or updates a previously published RFC or RFCs,
this information is included in the document header.  For example:</t>
          <t>"Updates: nnnn" or "Updates: nnnn, ..., nnnn"</t>
          <t>"Obsoletes: nnnn" or "Obsoletes: nnnn, ..., nnnn"</t>
          <t>If the document updates or obsoletes more than one document, numbers
will be listed in ascending order.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="full-title" toc="default">
        <name>Document Title</name>
        <t>The title must be centered below the rest of the heading, preceded by
two blank lines and followed by one blank line.</t>
        <t>Choosing a good title for an RFC can be a challenge.  A good title
should fairly represent the scope and purpose of the document without
being either too general or too specific and lengthy.</t>
        <t>Abbreviations in a title must generally be expanded when first
encountered (see Section 3.6 for additional guidance on
abbreviations).</t>
        <t>It is often helpful to follow the expansion with the parenthesized
abbreviation, as in the following example:</t>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                  Encoding Rules for the
  Common Routing Encapsulation Extension Protocol (CREEP)
]]></artwork>
        <t>The RFC Editor recommends that documents describing a particular
company's private protocol should bear a title of the form "Foo's ...
Protocol" (where Foo is a company name), to clearly differentiate it
from a protocol of more general applicability.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="abstract-section" toc="default">
        <name>Abstract Section</name>
        <t>  Every RFC must have an Abstract that provides a concise and comprehensive
overview of the purpose and contents of the entire document, to give a
technically knowledgeable reader a general overview of the function of the
document and some context with regards to its relationship (in particular,
whether it updates or obsoletes) any other RFCs.  In addition to its function in
the RFC itself, the Abstract section text will appear in publication
announcements and in the online index of RFCs.</t>
        <t>  Composing a useful Abstract generally requires thought and care. Usually,
an Abstract should begin with a phrase like "This memo ..." or "This document ..."
A satisfactory Abstract can often be constructed in part from material within
the Introduction section, but an effective Abstract may be shorter, less
detailed, and perhaps broader in scope than the Introduction.  Simply copying
and pasting the first few paragraphs of the Introduction is allowed, but it may
result in an Abstract that is overly long, incomplete, and redundant.</t>
        <t>  An Abstract is not a substitute for an Introduction; the RFC should be
self-contained as if there were no Abstract. Similarly, the Abstract should be
complete in itself.  Given that the Abstract will appear independently in
announcements and indices, mentions of other RFCs within the Abstract should
include both an RFC number and either the full or short title.  Any  documents
that are Updated or Obsoleted by the RFC must be mentioned in the  Abstract if those
documents offer important provisions of, or reasons for, the RFC.
These may be presented in a list format if that improves readability.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="rfc-editor-or-stream-notes-section" toc="default">
        <name>RFC Editor or Stream Notes Section</name>
        <t>A stream-approving body may approve the inclusion of an editorial
note to explain anything unusual about the process that led to the
document's publication or to note a correction.  In this case, a
stream note section will contain such a note.</t>
        <t>Additionally, an RFC Editor Note section may contain a note inserted
by the RFC Editor to highlight special circumstances surrounding
an RFC.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="status-of-this-memo-section" toc="default">
        <name>Status of This Memo Section</name>
        <t>The RFC Editor will supply an appropriate "Status of This Memo" as
defined in RFC  [RFC7841] and "Format for RFCs in the IAB Stream"
<xref target="IAB-FORM" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="copyright-licenses-and-ipr-boilerplate-section" toc="default">
        <name>Copyright, Licenses, and IPR Boilerplate Section</name>
        <t>The full copyright and license notices are available on the IETF
Trust Legal Provisions documents website <xref target="IETF-TRUST" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="toc-section" toc="default">
        <name>Table of Contents Section</name>
        <t>A Table of Contents (TOC) is required in all RFCs.  It must be
positioned after the Copyright Notice and before the Introduction.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="body-of-the-memo" toc="default">
        <name>Body of the Memo</name>
        <t>Following the TOC is the body of the memo.</t>
        <t>Each RFC must include an Introduction section that (among other
things) explains the motivation for the RFC and (if appropriate)
describes the applicability of the document, e.g., whether it
specifies a protocol, provides a discussion of some problem, is
simply of interest to the Internet community, or provides a status
report on some activity.  The body of the memo and the Abstract must
be self-contained and separable.  This may result in some duplication
of text between the Abstract and the Introduction; this is
acceptable.</t>
        <section anchor="introduction-section" toc="default">
          <name>Introduction Section</name>
          <t>The Introduction section should always be the first section following
the TOC (except in the case of MIB module documents).  While
"Introduction" is recommended, authors may choose alternate titles
such as "Overview" or "Background".  These alternates are acceptable.</t>
          <t>For MIB module documents, common practice has been for "The
Internet-Standard Management Framework" <xref target="MIB-BOILER" format="default"/> text to appear
as Section 1.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="requirements-language-section" toc="default">
          <name>Requirements Language Section</name>
          <t>Some documents use certain capitalized words ("MUST", "SHOULD", etc.)
to specify precise requirement levels for technical features.
<xref target="RFC2119"/> and <xref target="RFC8174"/> define a default interpretation of these
capitalized words in IETF documents.  If this interpretation is used,
RFCs 2119 and 8174 must be cited (as specified in RFCs 2119 and 8174) and included as a
normative reference.  Otherwise, the correct interpretation must be
specified in the document.</t>
          <t>This section must appear as part of the body of the memo (as defined
by this document).  It must appear as part of, or subsequent to, the
Introduction section.</t>
          <t>These words are considered part of the technical content of the
document and are intended to provide guidance to implementers about
specific technical features, generally governed by considerations of
interoperability.  RFC 2119 says:</t>
          <t>Imperatives of the type defined in this memo must be used with
   care and sparingly.  In particular, they MUST only be used where
   it is actually required for interoperation or to limit behavior
   which has potential for causing harm (e.g., limiting
   retransmisssions)  For example, they must not be used to try to
   impose a particular method on implementers where the method is not
   required for interoperability.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="iana-considerations-section" toc="default">
          <name>IANA Considerations Section</name>
          <t>For guidance on how to register IANA-related values or create new
registries to be managed by IANA, see "Guidelines for Writing an IANA
Considerations Section in RFCs" <xref target="BCP26" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>The RFC Editor will update text accordingly after the IANA
assignments have been made.  It is helpful for authors to clearly
identify where text should be updated to reflect the newly assigned
values.  For example, the use of "TBD1", "TBD2", etc., is recommended
in the IANA Considerations section and in the body of the memo.</t>
          <t>If the authors have provided values to be assigned by IANA, the
RFC Editor will verify that the values inserted by the authors match
those that have actually been registered on the IANA site.  When
writing a given value, consistent use of decimal or hexadecimal is
recommended.</t>
          <t>If any of the IANA-related information is not clear, the RFC Editor
will work with IANA to send queries to the authors to ensure that
assignments and values are properly inserted.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="internationalization-considerations-section" toc="default">
          <name>Internationalization Considerations Section</name>
          <t>All RFCs that deal with internationalization issues should have a
section describing those issues; see "IETF Policy on Character Sets
and Languages" <xref target="BCP18" format="default"/>, Section 6, for more information.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="security-considerations-section" toc="default">
          <name>Security Considerations Section</name>
          <t>All RFCs must contain a section that discusses the security
considerations relevant to the specification; see "Guidelines for
Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations" <xref target="BCP72" format="default"/> for more
information.</t>
          <t>Note that additional boilerplate material for RFCs containing MIB and
YANG modules also exists.  See "Security Guidelines for IETF MIB
Modules" <xref target="MIB-SEC" format="default"/> and "yang module security considerations"
<xref target="YANG-SEC" format="default"/> for details.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="references-section" toc="default">
          <name>References Section</name>
          <t>The reference list is solely for recording reference entries.
Introductory text or annotations beyond necessary translations <xref target="RFC7997" format="default"/> are not allowed.</t>
          <t>The RFC style allows the use of any of a variety of reference styles,
as long as they are used consistently within a document.  However,
where necessary, some reference styles have been described for use
within the Series.  See the following subsections as well as the References
section of this document.</t>
          <t>Reference lists must indicate whether each reference is normative or
informative, where normative references are essential to implementing
or understanding the content of the RFC and informative references
provide additional information.  More information about normative and
informative references may be found in the IESG's statement
"Normative and Informative References" <xref target="REFS" format="default"/>.  When both normative
and informative references exist, the references section should be
split into two subsections:</t>
          <t>Templates are available on the RFC Editor website for the XML format of
  certain references <xref target="REFEXAMPLE" format="default"/>.</t>
          <t>s.  References</t>
          <t>s.1.  Normative References</t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        xxx
        ...
        xxx
]]></artwork>
          <t>s.2.  Informative References</t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        xxx
        ...
        xxx
]]></artwork>
          <t>References will generally appear in alphanumeric order by citation
tag.  Where there are only normative or informative references, no
subsection is required; the top-level section should say "Normative
References" or "Informative References".</t>
          <t>Normative references to Internet-Drafts will cause publication of the
RFC to be suspended until the referenced draft is also ready for
publication; the RFC Editor will then update the entry to refer to
the RFC and publish both documents simultaneously.</t>
          <section anchor="referencing-rfcs" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing RFCs</name>
            <t>The following format is required for referencing RFCs. The Stream
  abbreviation should be used; when no stream is available, as with legacy RFCs,
  this may be left blank. </t>
            <t>Note the ordering for multiple authors: the format of
  the name of the last author listed is different than that of all previous
  authors in the list.</t>
            <t>For one author or editor:</t>
            <t>[RFCXXXX] Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable),
             "RFC Title", Stream, Sub-series number (if applicable),
             RFC number, RFC DOI, Date of publication,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc#">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc#&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[RFC3080] Rose, M., "The Blocks Extensible Exchange
             Protocol Core," IETF, RFC 3080, DOI 10.17487/RFC3080, March 2001,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3080">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3080&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>[RFC8157] Leymann, N., Heidemann, C., Zhang, M., Sarikaya, B., and M.
             Cullen, "Huawei's GRE Tunnel Bonding Protocol", independent,
            RFC 8157, DOI 10.17487/RFC8157, May 2017,
            <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8157">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8157&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>For two authors or editors:</t>
            <t>[RFCXXXX] Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable)
             and First initial. Last name, Ed. (if applicable),
             "RFC Title", Stream, Sub-series number (if applicable),
             RFC number, RFC DOI, Date of publication,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc#">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc#&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[RFC6323] Renker, G. and G. Fairhurst, "Sender RTT
             Estimate Option for the Datagram Congestion
             Control Protocol (DCCP)", IETF, RFC 6323, DOI 10.17487/RFC6323, July 2011,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6323">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6323&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>For three or more authors or editors:</t>
            <t>[RFCXXXX] Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable),
             Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable),
             and First initial. Last name, Ed. (if applicable),
             "RFC Title", Stream, Sub-series number (if applicable),
             RFC number, RFC DOI, Date of publication,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc#">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc#&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[RFC6429] Bashyam, M., Jethanandani, M., and A. Ramaiah,
             "TCP Sender Clarification for Persist
             Condition", IETF, RFC 6429, DOI 10.17487/RFC6429, December 2011,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6429">&gt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6429 &lt;</eref>.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="referencing-stds-and-bcps" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing RFC(s) in a Subseries (STDs, BCPs, and FYIs</name>
            <t>Internet Standards (STDs) and Best Current Practices (BCPs) may consist of
a single RFC or multiple RFCs.  Authors should carefully consider whether they
want to point the reader to the specific RFC or the sub series group.  In the
former case, references should appear as described in Section
4.8.6.2.  In the latter case, the sub series number should take precedence as,
for example, the citation tag, even in cases where the sub series currently
contains only one RFC.</t>
            <t>When an STD or BCP that contains multiple RFCs is referenced as a sub series
group, the reference entry should include ALL of the RFCs comprising that
sub-series in a reference grouping under a single citation tag [is it helpful to
point them to 7991 or the like on how to do this here?].  The authors should
refer to the specific RFC numbers as part of the text in the body of the
document and cite the sub series number (for example, "see RFC 2026 of
[BCP9]").  Inclusion of the URI to the STD or BCP info page (see Section 3.2.3
of [RFC5741]) is recommended.  The text should appear as follows:</t>
            <t>See RFC 1034 [STD13].</t>
            <t>For an STD or BCP that contains one RFC:</t>
            <t>[STDXXX]  Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable), "RFC
             Title", Stream, Sub-series number, RFC number, RFC DOI, Date of
             publication, <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std#">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std#&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[STD72]   Gellens, R. and J. Klensin, "Message Submission
             for Mail", IETF, STD 72, RFC 6409, DOI 10.17487/RFC6409, November 2011,
             <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std72">&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std72&gt;</eref>.</t>
            <t>For an STD or BCP that contains two or more RFCs:</t>
            <t>[STDXXX]  Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable),
             "RFC Title", Stream, Sub-series number, RFC number, RFC DOI, Date
             of publication.</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
         Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable)
         and First initial. Last name, Ed. (if applicable),
         "RFC Title", Stream, Sub-series number, RFC number, RFC DOI,
         Date of publication.

         <https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std#>
]]></artwork>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[STD13]   Mockapetris, P., "Domain names - concepts and
             facilities", IETF, STD 13, RFC 1034, November 1987.</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
  Mockapetris, P., "Domain names - implementation and
  specification", IETF, STD 13, RFC 1035, DOI 10.17487/RFC1035,
  November 1987.

         <https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std13>
]]></artwork>
            <t>Note - some RFCs contain an FYI sub-series number <xref target="FYI90" format="default"/> however, the FYI
series was ended by RFC 6360.  RFCs that were published with an FYI sub-series
number and still maintain the FYI number must include the sub-series number in
the reference and may otherwise be treated in the same manner as STDs and
BCPs.</t>
            <t>Grouping references to RFCs or other materials that are not part of a
   sub-series is discouraged.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="referencing-internet-drafts" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing Internet-Drafts</name>
            <t>References to Internet Drafts may only appear as informative
references.  Given that several revisions of an I-D may be produced
in a short time frame, references must include the posting date
(month and year), the full Internet-Draft file name (including the
version number), and the phrase "Internet Draft".  Authors may
reference multiple versions of an I-D.  If the referenced I-D was
also later published as an RFC, then that RFC must also be listed.
	    The reference should include a stable URL for the draft, if available.</t>
            <t>[SYMBOLIC-TAG]  Last name, First initial., Ed. (if applicable)
                   and First initial. Last name, Ed. (if
                   applicable), "I-D Title", Work in Progress, Internet-Draft,
                   draft-string-NN, Day Month Year, https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-something.
</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[RFC-STYLE] Flanagan, H. and S. Ginoza, "RFC Style Guide", Work in Progress,
               Internet-Draft, draft-flanagan-style-04,
               27 September 2019, https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-flanagan-style-04.
</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="referencing-errata" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing Errata</name>
            <t>The following format is required when a reference to an erratum
report is necessary:</t>
            <t>[ErrNumber]  RFC Errata, Erratum ID number, RFC number, &lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/errata/eid#&gt;.</t>
            <t>[Err1912]  RFC Errata, Erratum ID 1912, RFC 2978, &lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/errata/eid1912&gt;.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="referencing-IANA" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing IANA Registries</name>
            <t>IANA registries may appear in normative or informative reference sections.
            </t>
            <t>[IANA-SYMBOLIC-TAG]
            </t>
            <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
              <li> IANA, "Registry Name", &lt;URL&gt;.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="referencing-other-standards-development-organizations-sdos" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing Other Standards Development Organizations (SDOs)</name>
            <t>The following format is suggested when referencing a document or
standard from another SDO in which authors are listed:</t>
            <t>[SYMBOLIC-TAG]
            </t>
            <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
              <li> Last name, First initial. and First initial. Last name,</li>
              <li> "Document Title", Document reference number, Date of </li>
              <li> publication, &lt;URI if available&gt;.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>[W3C.REC-xml11]
            </t>
            <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
              <li> Bray, T., Paoli, J., Sperberg-McQueen, C., Maler, E.,</li>
              <li> Yergeau, F., and J.  Cowan, "Extensible Markup Language</li>
              <li> (XML) 1.1 (Second Edition)", W3C Recommendation</li>
              <li> REC-xml11-20060816, August 2006, </li>
              <li> &lt;https://www.w3.org/TR/2006/REC-xml11-20060816&gt;.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>The order of authors in the list is the same as the order
shown on the actual document and that the common, abbreviated form of
the SDO is used.</t>
            <t>Alternatively, when no list of authors is available, the following
format is recommended:</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[[SYMBOLIC-TAG]  Organization, "Document Title", Document
                   reference number, Date of publication,
                   <URI if available>.
]]></artwork>
            <t>Example (undated; see note below):</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[[IEEE.802.15.4]
           IEEE, "IEEE Standard for Low-Rate Wireless Networks",
           IEEE 802.15.4,
           <https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/7460875/>.
]]></artwork>
            <t>Example (dated; see note below):</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[[IEEE802.1Q]  IEEE, "Local and Metropolitan Area
                 Networks -- Media Access Control (MAC)
                 Bridges and Virtual Bridged Local Area
                 Networks", IEEE Std 802.1Q-2011, August 2011,
                 <https://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/
                 802.1Q-2011.html>
]]></artwork>
            <t>Per the IEEE coordination team, listing dates for IEEE standards is not
recommended unless there is a need to cite a particular section, in which case
the dated reference is appropriate. An RFC with a dated IEEE reference suggests
that the RFC only applies to that specific IEEE specification.</t>
          </section>
          <section anchor="uris-in-rfcs" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing Webpages</name>
            <t>References to webpages acceptable in either the normative or informative
  sections, as long as the URL provided is the most stable (i.e., unlikely to
  change and expected to be continuously available) and direct reference
  possible.  The URL will be verified as valid during the RFC editorial process.</t>
            <t>If a dated URI (one that includes a timestamp for the page) is
available for a referenced web page, its use is required.</t>
            <t>Note that the URL may not be the sole information provided for a
reference entry.</t>
            <t>The use of HTTPS rather than HTTP is strongly encouraged.</t>
            <t>Example:</t>
            <t>[SYMBOLIC-TAG]  Author (if available), "Page Title (if available)", &lt;URL&gt;.</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[[ISOC-MANRS]  Internet Society, "Mutually Agreed
                 Norms for Routing Security",
                 <https://www.internetsociety.org/issues/manrs>
]]></artwork>
          </section>
          <section anchor="emailref" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing Email on Mailing Lists</name>
            <t>When referencing emails to mailing lists, the template provided here should be used:
            </t>
            <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
              <li>[reftag] Sender, A., "Subject: Subject line", message to the </li>
              <li>listname mailing list, DD Month YYYY, &lt;URL&gt;.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="repositories" toc="default">
            <name>Referencing Code Repositories</name>
            <t>References to online code repositories such as GitHub or SourceForge
    should be used as informative references only. The reference entry should
    include the repository title, commit hash or similar release marker if
    available, date of last commit, and URL.</t>
            <t>Examples:</t>
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[[pysaml] "Python implementation of SAML2", commit 7135d53,
      6 March 2018, <https://github.com/IdentityPython/pysaml2>.

      [linuxlite] "Linux Lite", 9 March 2018,
                  <https://sourceforge.net/projects/linuxlite/>.
      ]]></artwork>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="appendices-section" toc="default">
        <name>Appendices Section</name>
        <t>The RFC Editor recommends placing references before the Appendices.
Appendices should be labeled as "Appendix A.  Title", "A.1.  Title",
"Appendix B.  Title", etc.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="acknowledgements-section" toc="default">
        <name>Acknowledgements Section</name>
        <t>This optional section may be used instead of, or in addition to, a
Contributors section.  It is often used by authors to publicly thank
those who have provided feedback regarding a document and to note any
documents from which text was borrowed.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="contributors-section" toc="default">
        <name>Contributors Section</name>
        <t>This optional section acknowledges those who have made significant
contributions to the document.</t>
        <t>In a similar fashion to the Author's Address section, the RFC Editor
does not make the determination as to who should be listed as a
contributor to an RFC.  The determination of who should be listed as
a contributor is made by the stream.</t>
        <t>The Contributors section may include brief statements about the
nature of particular contributions (e.g., "Sam contributed Section 3"), and
it may also include affiliations of listed contributors.  At the
discretion of the author(s), contact addresses may also be included
in the Contributors section, for those contributors whose knowledge
makes them useful future contacts for information about the RFC.  The
format of any contact information should be similar to the format of
information in the Author's Address section.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="index" toc="default">
        <name>Index</name>
        <t>If included, an index appears at the end of the document, immediately
    before Author's Address section. </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="authors-address-or-authors-addresses-section" toc="default">
        <name>Author's Address or Authors' Addresses Section</name>
        <t>This required section gives contact information for the author(s)
   listed in the first-page header.</t>
        <t>Contact information must include a long-lived email address and
   optionally may include a postal address and/or telephone number.  If
   the postal address is included, it should include the country name,
   using the English short name listed by the ISO 3166 Maintenance
   Agency <xref target="ISO_OBP" format="default"/>.  The purpose of this section is to
   (1) unambiguously define author identity (e.g., the John Smith who
   works for FooBar Systems) and (2) provide contact information for
   future readers who have questions or comments.</t>
        <t>The practice of munged email addresses (i.e., altering an email
   address to make it less readable to bots and web crawlers to avoid
   spam) is not appropriate in an archival document series.  Author
   contact information is provided so that readers can easily contact
   the author with questions and/or comments.  Address munging is not
   allowed in RFCs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no security considerations.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="changelog" toc="default">
      <name>Change Log</name>
      <t>This section to be removed before publication.
      </t>
      <ul empty="true" spacing="normal">
        <li>-00 to -01: Citation tag requirements more tightly specified; index
      moved; new errata URI added; capitalization of working/research group
      specified</li>
        <li>-01 to -02: update Abstract guidance </li>
        <li>-02 to -03: updated citation section; changed list styles; added angle
      brackets to reference examples; changed I-D reference format; clarified
      sub-series reference format; added guidance on referencing code
      repositories</li>
        <li>-03 to -04: updated Reference Section guidance; added information on alt text</li>
        <li>-04 to -05: change author, add acknowledgement</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="STYLE-WEB" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc-style-guide/part2.html">
          <front>
            <title>Web Portion of the Style Guide</title>
            <author>
              <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
	      
        <reference anchor="ABBR" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc-style-guide/abbrev.expansion.txt">
          <front>
            <title>RFC Editor Abbreviations List</title>
            <author>
              <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ALTTEXT" target="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/info-and-relationships">
          <front>
            <title>Understanding Success Criterion 1.3.1: Info and Relationships</title>
            <author>
              <organization>W3C</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>

<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>	      

<referencegroup anchor="BCP9" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp9">
  <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2223.xml"/>
  <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5657.xml"/>
  <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6410.xml"/>
  <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7100.xml"/>
     <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7127.xml"/>
     <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7475.xml"/>
        <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8789.xml"/>
           <xi:include
   href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9282.xml"/>
</referencegroup>


        <reference anchor="BCP18" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp18">
          <front>
            <title>IETF Policy on Character Sets and Languages</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="Harald Alvestrand"/>
            <date year="1998" month="January"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="18"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2277"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="BCP26" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp26">
          <front>
            <title>Guidelines for Writing an ANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand" fullname="Harald Alvestrand"/>
            <author initials="T." surname="Narten"/>
            <date year="2008" month="May"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="BCP32" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp32">
          <front>
            <title>Reserved Top Level DNS Names</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="Eastlake 3rd"/>
            <author initials="A." surname="Panitz"/>
            <date year="1999" month="June"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="32"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2606"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="BCP72" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp72">
          <front>
            <title>Guidelines for Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations</title>
            <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla"/>
            <author initials="B." surname="Korver"/>
            <date year="2003" month="July"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="72"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3552"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CLUSTER" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/cluster_def.html">
          <front>
            <title>Clusters in the RFC Editor Queue</title>
            <author>
              <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="CMOS">
          <front>
            <title>Chicago Manual of Style, 16th ed.</title>
            <author>
              <organization>University of Chicago Press, 2010</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2010"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="FYI90" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/fyi90">
          <front>
            <title>FYI on FYI: Introduction to the FYI Notes</title>
            <author initials="G." surname="Malkin"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Reynolds"/>
            <date year="1990" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="FYI" value="90"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1150"/>
          <annotation>
          Housley, R., "Conclusion of FYI RFC Sub-Series", RFC 6360,
          August 2011.
          </annotation>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IAB-FORM" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc-style-guide/iab-format.txt">
          <front>
            <title>Format for RFCs in the IAB Stream</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IAB</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ID-GUIDE" target="https://www.ietf.org/ietf-ftp/1id-guidelines.txt">
          <front>
            <title>Guidelines to Authors of Internet Drafts</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="IETF-TRUST" target="https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info/">
          <front>
            <title>Trust Legal Provisions (TLP)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF Trust</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ISO_OBP" target="https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/">
          <front>
            <title>Online Browsing Platform (OBP)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ISO</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="ISO3297">
          <front>
            <title>Identification and description, Information and documentation - International standard serial number (ISSN)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Technical Committee ISO/TC 46, Information and documentation, Subcommittee SC 9
              </organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2007" month="September"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="MIB-BOILER" target="https://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-boilerplate.html">
          <front>
            <title>Boilerplate for IETF MIB Documents</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF OPS Area</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="MIB-SEC" target="https://trac.tools.ietf.org/area/ops/trac/wiki/mib-security">
          <front>
            <title>Security Guidelines for IETF MIB Modules</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF OPS Area</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="REFEXAMPLE" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/ref-example/">
          <front>
            <title>Reference Examples</title>
            <author>
              <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="REFS" target="https://www.ietf.org/iesg/statement/normative-informative.html">
          <front>
            <title>IESG Statement: Normative and Informative</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IESG</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC4844" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4844" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4844.xml">
          <front>
            <title>The RFC Series and RFC Editor</title>
            <author initials="L." surname="Daigle" fullname="L. Daigle" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author>
              <organization>Internet Architecture Board</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2007" month="July"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This document describes the framework for an RFC Series and an RFC Editor function that incorporate the principles of organized community involvement and accountability that has become necessary as the Internet technical community has grown, thereby enabling the RFC Series to continue to fulfill its mandate.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4844"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC4844"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7841" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7841" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7841.xml">
          <front>
            <title>RFC Streams, Headers, and Boilerplates</title>
            <author initials="J." surname="Halpern" fullname="J. Halpern" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="L." surname="Daigle" fullname="L. Daigle" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="O. Kolkman" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2016" month="May"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>RFC documents contain a number of fixed elements such as the title page header, standard boilerplates, and copyright/IPR statements. This document describes them and introduces some updates to reflect current usage and requirements of RFC publication.  In particular, this updated structure is intended to communicate clearly the source of RFC creation and review.  This document obsoletes RFC 5741, moving detailed content to an IAB web page and preparing for more flexible output formats.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7841"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7841"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC6635" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6635" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6635.xml">
          <front>
            <title>RFC Editor Model (Version 2)</title>
            <author initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="O. Kolkman" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Halpern" fullname="J. Halpern" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author>
              <organization>IAB</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2012" month="June"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>The RFC Editor model described in this document divides the responsibilities for the RFC Series into three functions: the RFC Series Editor, the RFC Production Center, and the RFC Publisher. Internet Architecture Board (IAB) oversight via the RFC Series Oversight Committee (RSOC) is described, as is the relationship between the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC) and the RSOC.  This document reflects the experience gained with "RFC Editor Model (Version 1)", documented in RFC 5620, and obsoletes that document.  This document is not an Internet Standards Track  specification; it is published for informational purposes.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6635"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6635"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7990" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7990" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7990.xml">
          <front>
            <title>RFC Format Framework</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="H. Flanagan">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2016" month="December"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>In order to improve the readability of RFCs while supporting their archivability, the canonical format of the RFC Series will be transitioning from plain-text ASCII to XML using the xml2rfc version 3 vocabulary; different publication formats will be rendered from that base document.  With these changes comes an increase in complexity for authors, consumers, and the publisher of RFCs.  This document serves as the framework that provides the problem statement, lays out a road map of the documents that capture the specific requirements, and describes the transition plan.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7990"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7990"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7991" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7991" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7991.xml">
          <front>
            <title>The "xml2rfc" Version 3 Vocabulary</title>
            <author initials="P." surname="Hoffman" fullname="P. Hoffman">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2016" month="December"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This document defines the "xml2rfc" version 3 vocabulary: an XML-based language used for writing RFCs and Internet-Drafts.  It is heavily derived from the version 2 vocabulary that is also under discussion.  This document obsoletes the v2 grammar described in RFC 7749.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7991"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7991"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7996" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7996" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7996.xml">
          <front>
            <title>SVG Drawings for RFCs: SVG 1.2 RFC</title>
            <author initials="N." surname="Brownlee" fullname="N. Brownlee">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2016" month="December"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>This document specifies SVG 1.2 RFC -- an SVG profile for use in diagrams that may appear in RFCs -- and considers some of the issues concerning the creation and use of such diagrams.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7996"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7996"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="RFC7997" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7997" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7997.xml">
          <front>
            <title>The Use of Non-ASCII Characters in RFCs</title>
            <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="H. Flanagan" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2016" month="December"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>In order to support the internationalization of protocols and a more diverse Internet community, the RFC Series must evolve to allow for the use of non-ASCII characters in RFCs.  While English remains the required language of the Series, the encoding of future RFCs will be in UTF-8, allowing for a broader range of characters than typically used in the English language.  This document describes the RFC Editor requirements and gives guidance regarding the use of non-ASCII characters in RFCs.</t>
              <t>This document updates RFC 7322.  Please view this document in PDF form to see the full text.</t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7997"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7997"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="STD66" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/std66">
          <front>
            <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
            <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Fielding"/>
            <author initials="L." surname="Masinter"/>
            <date year="2005" month="January"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="TERMS" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/styleguide.html">
          <front>
            <title>Terms List</title>
            <author>
              <organization>RFC Editor</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="YANG-SEC" target="https://trac.tools.ietf.org/area/ops/trac/wiki/yang-security-guidelines">
          <front>
            <title>yang module security considerations</title>
            <author>
              <organization>IETF Ops Area</organization>
            </author>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
	<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7669.xml"/>
	      
	<reference anchor="RFC2223bis" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-rfc-editor-rfc2223bis-08">
     <front>
       <title>Instructions to Request for Comments (RFC) Authors</title>
       <author initials="J." surname="Reynolds" fullname="Joyce K. Reynolds" role="editor">
         <organization />
       </author>
       <author initials="R." surname="Braden" fullname="Robert Braden" role="editor">
         <organization />
       </author>
       <date day="1" month="August" year="2004" />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-rfc-editor-rfc2223bis-08"/>
   </reference>	   
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="app-A" toc="default">
      <name>Related Procedures</name>
      <t>The following procedures are related to the application and updating
   of the RFC Style Guide.</t>
      <section anchor="app-a1" toc="default">
        <name>Dispute Resolution</name>
        <t>There are competing rationales for some of the rules described in
   this Guide, and the RFC Editor has selected the ones that work best
   for the Series.  However, at times, an author may have a disagreement
   with the RFC Production Center (RPC) over the application of Style
   Guide conventions.  In such cases, the authors should discuss their
   concerns with the RPC.  If no agreement can be reached between the
   RPC and the authors, the RFC Series Editor will, with input from the
   appropriate stream-approving body, make a final determination.  If
   further resolution is required, the dispute resolution process as
   described in the RFC Editor Model <xref target="RFC6635" format="default"/> will be followed.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="app-a2" toc="default">
        <name>Returning an I-D to the Document Stream</name>
        <t>For a given document, if the RFC Editor determines that it cannot be
   edited without serious risk of altering the meaning of the technical
   content or if the RFC Editor does not have the resources to provide
   the level of editing it needs, it may be sent back to the stream-
   approving body with a request to improve the clarity, consistency,
   and/or readability of the document.  This is not to be considered a
   dispute with the author.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="app-a3" toc="default">
        <name>Revising This Document and Associated Web Pages</name>
        <t>The RFC Series is continually evolving as a document series.  This
   document focuses on the fundamental and stable requirements that must
   be met by an RFC.  From time to time, the RFC Editor may offer less
   formal recommendations that authors may apply at their discretion;
   these recommendations may be found on the RFC Editor website
   "Guidelines for RFC Style" <xref target="STYLE-WEB" format="default"/>.</t>
        <t>When a new recommendation is made regarding the overall structure and
   formatting of RFCs, it will be published on that page and accepted
   for a period of time before the RFC Editor determines whether it
   should become part of the fundamental requirements in the RFC Style
   Guide or remain as a less formal recommendation.  That period of time
   will vary, in part depending on the frequency with which authors
   encounter and apply the guidance.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="app-b" toc="default">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>This document refers heavily to <xref target="RFC2223"/> and <xref target="RFC2223bis"/>; as such, we are grateful to the authors of those documents for putting their time and effort into the RFC Series.</t>
<t>Much of this document was written by Heather Flanagan during her term as the RFC Series Editor (RSE).</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
